Okay, moving on to testicular tumors.
My recommendation before you do this section
would be to make sure that you master the section
on female ovarian tumors.
And that's because once you understand ovarian tumors,
testicular tumors are all downhill.
Now, remember that in the female ovary,
we had three compartments that could lead to tumors.
We had the surface epithelium,
which created surface epithelial tumors.
We had the germ cell leading to germ cell tumors.
And then we had the sex cord stroma,
which was the connective and supportive tissue
of the ovary, which leads to sex cord stromal tumors.
Now, fortunately, within the testicle,
we don't have surface epithelium,
so that makes life a little easy.
And so, therefore, there are only two types
of testicular tumors.
There's the germ cell tumor
and then the sex cord stromal tumor.
Patients with testicular tumors,
they present with a firm, painless testicular mass.
And, of course, because it is a solid, firm mass,
it cannot be transluminated.
Again, this is in contrast to a hydrosoe,
which would be transluminated.
Now, one very high yield
and important point to recognize
is that testicular tumors are not biopsied.
This is against the general principle of medicine
where you always biopsy cancer
to prove that it's cancer
and to subtype the cancer.
However, in the case of the testicle,
this is not performed for two basic reasons.
Number one, if this is the testicle
sitting in the scrotum,
if a biopsy were performed,
you would pull the tumor out from the testicle
and potentially seed the scrotum.
And, of course, that would not be desirable.
So that's the first reason
why we don't biopsy testicular tumors.
The second reason why we don't biopsy testicular tumors
is that the vast majority of testicular tumors
are actually germ cell tumors.
In fact, greater than 95% of testicular tumors
are germ cell tumors,
and germ cell tumors are all malignant.
So, for all practical purposes,
the vast majority of testicular tumors are malignant.
Germ cell tumors, as I just mentioned,
are the most common type,
greater than 95% of testicular tumors.
They usually occur between the ages of 15 to 40.
Risk factors include cryptorchidism,
or an undescended testicle,
and Klinefelter syndrome.
Let's go back and just briefly remind ourselves,
as we spoke about when we talked about the female ovary,
that there are really five key germ cell tumors
to be familiar with at your level.
Remember that the germ cell has the ability
to make baby tissues,
and so therefore you can get tumors of baby-like tissues.
For example, the teratoma,
which would represent mature baby tissue,
and embryonal carcinoma,
which would represent embryo-like cells.
And then, in addition,
the germ cells have the ability to make placenta,
and when you get a tumor of placental tissue,
that's called a choriocarcinoma.
The germ cells also have the ability to make yolk sac,
and so when you get a tumor of yolk sac,
that's called a yolk sac tumor,
and finally, the germ cells have the ability
to make additional germ cells.
Now, in the ovary, that was called a dysgerminoma.
However, in the testicle,
that is called a seminoma,
seminoma,
as if it contains sperm,
or germ cell-like cells.
Now, in the case of germ cell tumors within the testicle,
remember that all are malignant,
and we divide germ cell tumors
into seminoma and non-seminoma,
and this is a major division
in our understanding of germ cell tumors,
and that's because seminoma usually responds to radiotherapy,
metastasizes late,
and has an excellent prognosis,
versus non-seminoma,
which has a variable response to treatment,
and metastasizes early.
So we're going to first start with seminoma.
Seminoma, of course, is a malignant tumor
of large cells with clear cytoplasm and central nuclei.
In fact, this description is very similar
to the description of dysgerminoma within the ovary,
and so seminoma in the testicle
equals dysgerminoma within the ovary.
Now, when a seminoma is present,
the gross examination of the testicle
will reveal a homogenous mass
with no hemorrhage or necrosis.
This is how yield examiners like to ask you this,
so that the mass itself will be homogenous
with no hemorrhage and no necrosis,
and I'll show you a picture of this in a moment.
Rare cases of seminoma can produce beta-HCG.
Now, remember that we classically associate beta-HCG
with choriocarcinoma or the tumor of placental tissue.
However, rare cases of seminoma can also produce beta-HCG,
and we have already discussed the fact
that seminoma has a good prognosis
and responds to radiotherapy.
Here's a picture of seminoma.
What we have here are large cells
with clear cytoplasm and central nuclei,
and, of course, the dysgerminoma in the ovary
would look very similar.
Here's the gross picture of a seminoma.
In seminoma, recall that it is a homogenous mass
with no hemorrhage and no necrosis.
And, again, examiners like you to know
that it is a homogenous mass
with no hemorrhage and no necrosis.
As far as the non-seminominus tumors are concerned,
the first that we'll discuss is embryonal carcinoma.
Remember that we're going to divide testicular tumors
into seminoma and non-seminoma.
So now we're talking about the non-seminomas.
The first would be embryonal carcinoma.
Again, this is a malignant tumor
of immature primitive cells.
Again, they're embryo-like, hence the word embryonal.
They're very primitive, like the cells of the embryo.
It is important to note,
and examiners like to press on this issue,
and that is that the tumor can form glands.
It's going to be a hemorrhagic mass with necrosis,
and that's because it's a primitive tumor
and is rapidly growing.
It'll be bloody.
It'll be necrotic.
This tumor is aggressive with early hematogenous spread.
Again, the cells are primitive and embryo-like,
and so they're genetically programmed
to move and spread rapidly.
When patients with embryonal carcinoma
are treated with chemotherapy,
an interesting thing that can occur
is that the tumor can differentiate.
So because these are very primitive embryo-like cells,
that tumor can actually become something more mature.
For example, chemotherapy can cause the embryonal carcinoma
to become a teratoma,
and that's particularly high yield
for board examinations as well.
Now, embryonal carcinoma is very primitive,
and it also has the ability
to secrete alpha-fetoprotein or beta-HCG,
and that, again, is important to note.
Classically, you would associate AFP with the Oaksac tumor,
and classically, you would associate beta-HCG
with choriocarcinoma, the tumor of placental tissue.
However, it's important to note
that embryonal carcinoma can secrete either AFP or beta-HCG.
Here's a picture of embryonal carcinoma.
You've got primitive cells,
and in this particular case, they're forming glands,
and I thought this was a perfect picture
because, again, examiners like you to know
that embryonal carcinoma does have the ability to form glands.
Here's a gross picture.
This is the tumor here in the testicle.
Again, this is the normal up here,
and you can clearly see that this is a hemorrhagic or bloody mass,
and, again, that's indicative
that you're dealing with a non-seminominus germ cell tumor,
and, in this particular case, embryonal carcinoma.
Oaksac tumor is a malignant tumor that resembles a yolk sac.
It's the most common testicular tumor in children.
That's how it yield.
So, for your purposes,
when you have a testicular tumor in a child,
for example, a five-year-old,
then you really want to consider yolk sac
on the top of your differential.
Now, of course, yolk sac tumor has the ability
to produce alpha-fetoprotein,
and so AFP is characteristically elevated in yolk sac tumors.
The characteristic histology of yolk sac tumor
is called a Schiller-Duvall body.
Now, this isn't the most common histology,
but it's the classic characteristic histology,
and, hence, it shows up on examinations.
This is also called a glomeruloid-like structure.
That's the way the examiners like to describe it.
Again, a glomeruloid-like structure.
And the idea here is that this sort of mimics the glomerulus.
Let's pretend that this is Bowman's capsule,
and this is Bowman's space,
and then this is the glomerulus
with a blood vessel running through it.
Again, it doesn't exactly look like the glomerulus,
but it's glomerulus-like,
and so, therefore, it's called a glomeruloid structure.
And, again, those are called Schiller-Duvall bodies,
and they're characteristic for yolk sac tumor.
Choriocarcinoma is a malignant tumor of placental-like tissue,
and so it contains the cells
that normally line the placental villi,
and those are syncytiotrophoblasts and cytotrophoblasts.
Now, remember that the syncytiotrophoblasts
are gonna make beta-HCG.
It's high yield to know that the beta-HCG
comes from the syncytiotrophoblast.
Now, when the beta-HCG is made by this tumor,
that's gonna result in elevation of the beta-HCG.
However, another important thing to remember
is that when you have a high beta-HCG,
the alpha subunit of HCG
is similar to the alpha subunits of FSH, LH, and TSH,
and therefore, patients can present with hyperthyroidism
because the HCG can activate the TSH receptor
or gynecomastia because the HCG can activate
the FSH and LH receptors,
and that's very high yield for the purposes of examinations.
Now, this tumor is going to produce
syncytiotrophoblasts and cytotrophoblasts,
so it mimics placental tissue.
However, remember that the functional unit
of the placenta was the villus,
so that when you look at a placenta,
you've got a villus with a blood vessel
running through the center,
and then you've got the syncytiotrophoblasts
and cytotrophoblasts growing around the edge.
However, in the case of choriocarcinoma,
it's very important to note that you don't get villi.
You only get the syncytiotrophoblasts
and the cytotrophoblasts.
Now, of course, syncytiotrophoblasts
and cytotrophoblasts are genetically programmed
to find blood vessels.
That's what the placenta does
when it implants into the uterine wall.
And so this tumor will metastasize
very early via the blood.
In fact, one of the characteristics of this tumor
is that you tend to have a tiny primary
within the testicle
and then massive tumor
throughout the rest of the body.
And that's a little bit against the convention
when we think about cancer.
Remember, if the patient's got, for example,
a large breast mass
and a tiny mass in the liver,
then we would assume that the breast mass is the primary
and that the tiny mass in the liver
is probably metastatic from the breast.
However, in this particular case,
you have a tiny mass in the testicle
and massive disease throughout the rest of the body.
But because you know that choriocarcinoma
rapidly goes into the blood,
you can assume that the primary
is actually in the testicle.
So again, that's important to note as well.
Here's a picture of choriocarcinoma.
These are the cytotrophoblasts
and these larger cells, multinucleated,
are the syncytiotrophoblasts.
And again, there would be no villi
produced by this particular tumor.
Teratoma is the final germ cell tumor.
This is a tumor of mature fetal tissue.
It's derived from two or three embryonic layers.
Now, very high yield to note,
teratoma was benign in females.
However, in males, it is malignant.
All right, teratoma is benign in females.
And teratoma can also produce AFP or beta-8CG.
So these are a few high yields
to be aware of concerning teratoma.
Now, although we spend so much time
dividing germ cell tumors
into these very distinct categories,
the vast majority of germ cell tumors
are usually mixed.
So, for example, a patient can have
a yolk sac tumor plus a choriocarcinoma
or a teratoma plus a seminoma.
And so it's important to remember
that most germ cell tumors in the testicle
are actually mixed.
And the prognosis is based on the worst component.
So, for example, if you have a seminoma
and associated with that seminoma
is a choriocarcinoma,
then the prognosis would be based
on the choriocarcinoma.
Sex-cord stromal tumors
are the second category of tumor
that can arise within the testicle.
These tumors resemble
the normal sex-cord stromal tissues
of the testicle and are usually benign.
Here's an image of the normal testicle
just to remind you of the sex-cord stromal tissues.
So the sex-cord includes the Sertoli cells.
And remember that the Sertoli cells
are the cells that line the tubules.
And, of course, this area here is the tubule.
So you could potentially get a Sertoli cell tumor.
At the same time, you've got these pink cells
in between the tubules,
which are called lydic cells.
And so you can also develop a lydic cell tumor.
Now, lydic cell tumors usually produce androgen.
And so because they produce androgen,
you're going to get precocious puberty in children,
or it could also result in gynecomastia in adults.
One of the characteristics on histology
of a lydic cell tumor
is that you see these crystals within the cells.
And these are called rinky crystals.
And that's, again, how you'll to know
that lydic cell tumors often have rinky crystals.
Sertoli cell tumors will be composed of tubules.
And, of course, the Sertoli cells
are the cells that normally line the tubules.
So the tumor of Sertoli cells
will also form tubules.
And these are usually clinically silent.
The final point to make in this section
is that when you have a testicular mass
in the testicle,
it's, of course, usually a germ cell tumor.
But that germ cell tumors normally occur
between the age of 15 to 40.
If you have a testicular tumor in a male
greater than the age of 60, for example,
then the most common cause would be lymphoma.
Again, it's important to note the age of the patient.
Between 15 to 40, you think about germ cell tumors.
But greater than the age of 60,
the more common cause of a testicular mass is lymphoma.
This is usually bilateral.
And the lymphoma that develops in the testicle
is usually a diffuse large B cell type of lymphoma.
And that concludes our section on testicular tumors.